Junkyard Love podcast. At what age do we
learn how to have better
comprehensive Junkyard Love podcast?
David Craig, welcome to the Junkyard
Love podcast, my brother. It's It's an
absolute pleasure to be here. Thank you
so much for agreeing to do this. Like I
I've said a million times, I'm over the
moon. I'm so excited. I love it. Thank
you, man. Thank you for the opportunity.
The pleasure is all mine, really. Yeah.
Just see seeing you again and seeing you
flourish is, you know, amazing to me.
Yeah. Yeah. It's a it's it's a beautiful
thing to be able to have have our
teachers on our Facebook still like it
sounds like this low like oh it's it's
kind of nice but it's actually very
beautiful. How does that feel for you as
a teacher to have your students in like
you know you have your couple years with
them and you get to know them
intricately and then you watch them grow
for 10 15 years later. What what is that
even like? Uh it's pretty amazing. Um, I
have about I think about 650 former
students on my Facebook and um, you
know, just see them flourish like you
said, see them have kids, be parents,
um, all that stuff. And, and what's
really cool through Facebook, I've kind
of been able to not only keep tabs on
them, but I've actually like visited
them and gone to their weddings and
things like that, you know? So, you
can't really put a value on that. I
mean, it's just amazing that you're able
to do that and you know, this technology
kind of gives us that opportunity, you
know, and uh you're right. You know, I
only knew him for a short couple of
years, but now, you know, some of them
are like 50 years old and stuff, you
know, they're grandparents. So, it's
it's really cool to see them, you know,
like progress through their own lives.
And of course, you know, there's a
double-edged sword to everything. And,
you know, unfortunately, some people
haven't made it that were my students.
And that's, you know, tragic, of course,
but uh, you know, that's kind of the way
life rolls. Yeah. Yeah. It's nice to be
able to have that open connection with
them and kind of like drop in and and
see what they're doing and and also, you
know, if they ever need some advice from
from old uh Mr. Craig, you know, they
can they have that open door. You know,
we have our magic rectangle that's just
an open window to to great great
perspective and advice if they want it.
You know, it's funny quite a few have
have taken advantage of that opportunity
over the years.
what what have they said like like what
are kind of the you don't have to share
like super details but like what what
what is the kind of thing that someone
approaches you with of like hey can I
get your perspective on this? Well, I
think you know, um, a lot of times it's
the posts that they make on and then I
kind of like throw out something to kind
of soothe their whatever is ailing them
or something like that and then they'll
message me privately and tell me this is
what's happened. You know, they'll tell
me something that's happened in their
life and then from there I just give
them kind of my perspective on it. And
at the very least, it kind of, you know,
gives them an opportunity to realize,
hey, this is going to pass. I can I'm I
have what it takes to get over this. And
I've talked some people off a ledge,
frankly. You know, they've just wanted
to throw up their hands and give up. And
and whatever encouraging word that I I
said to them ended up telling to take
the step towards the future, you know,
instead of just throwing up their hands
and giving up. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
that's that's a really powerful position
to to be in. Um I've had my own
instances of those same things. I was
just talking with a friend the other
day. He uh he texted me uh he's another
another Kelsea guy class 2010 and he
texted me this long text. He's like,
"Man, I just I was driving and uh it was
wet outside, you know, there was a big
puddle and he said he was about to smash
the puddle, but last second he noticed
that there was there was a guy that he
would have just totally douched if if he
hit it." And so he like kind of swerved
and he he like I guess he kind of made
eye contact with the guy of like I see
you you know and he kept going and then
he was he parked and he was going to the
gym or something and the guy approached
him and the guy was like held out his
hand and said hey man I just want to say
thank you for not splashing me like you
know it you didn't have to go out of
your way to not splash me and I noticed
that you did so so thank you and he kind
of expressed that he was having a tough
day and that like really helped him out.
So, it's just like, man, us just acting
off these like little intuitions of of
not even necessarily like I'm going to
save this guy's life, but just being
encouraging to someone or giving them
like a hey, you're you're okay is pretty
powerful stuff, you know? It could be
everything. It could be something so
small to us, natural to us a lot of the
times. Like a lot of us are so loving,
you know, if we just just lean into it a
little bit, you know, something so
little to us could be massive to someone
else, you know. Well, I think it's
really a surprise to them that I am
still monitoring them or following them
and you know, sometimes they say some
things that alarm me that realize that
they're hurting in some ways and uh just
the fact that you know that I can say
something to them, something positive,
which is what I used to do with them. I
said positive things back in the day and
of course you know they all trust me and
then they just they're okay after that.
Then they go forward, you know. Yeah.
And like you said, that positive thing.
I mean, you know, and I don't even a lot
of times try to solve their problem. I
just say, "Hey, listen. You can do this.
This is going to pass. This is kind of
the way things are, you know, you got
to, you know, keep going forward." And
then everything's cool. Yeah. Yeah. A
little encouragement goes a long way.
Yes. Especially from a from a figure
that they trust, you know. Um I So So
what was that like? I mean now and then
even you know when
you cuz cuz I think about me like my
sister and I were talking about you know
like we didn't we didn't necessarily at
that time we we certainly didn't have a
father figure that we you know and I
don't want to project like you you know
project father figuress all over you
know um but I wonder like do you do you
contemplate that like you know are you
aware when you're a teacher of hey I
kind of know that these kids don't
really have someone they're looking up
to at home so I'm going to lean in a
little more or is this Is this really
just like a non-intentional natural
state for you to be in? I guess like
what's what's that position like? So, I
think back in those days I made, you
know, my learning environment a safe
place for people to be. And, you know,
let's be honest, I wasn't attracting the
football player, cheerleader type, you
know, the ones that you would call the
cool kids, right? I attracted kids that
needed a place to be, a safe place, and
I provided that safe place. And man,
along the way, I made it super fun for
them, and they're like, "Whoa, this
dude, you know, he's making things safe
for me. He's there's no judgment here.
He doesn't allow it, you know, we're
kind of like this cool community. we
have our thing here, you know, and uh so
they, you know, word of mouth kind of
spread and the next thing you know, my
classes were bustling at the seams, you
know, and and you know, there were some
kids that I spent a lot of time with
more than others, like for example, your
sister. I mean, I spent a lot of time
with her cuz she helped me with almost
everything that had to do with the
technical side. I mean, I relied on her
heavily. In fact, there's many times I'd
tell her, "Hey, Katie, you got to go to
class sometime." You know, it's like you
can't. And I would have kids that would
show up that weren't, you know, like,
"Okay, why are you here? You should be
in another class." But they wanted to be
there. And, you know, I think pe I think
kids naturally saw me as that person
that they could look to, father figure,
whatever it
was. I don't think I leaned in anymore
for anybody unless they came to me and I
thought they needed that. So, yeah, it
just come it pretty much came naturally
for me, you know? everywhere I've gone.
It's a It's a It's a good place to be.
It's a like we were talking about before
and I probably said on this podcast a
bunch of times, we we're talking about
um you know how you can kind of work on
yourself in a way or like your
relationship with yourself allows you to
show up and then be an environment for
others to then do the same, you know?
And it's cool, you know, when you're a
teacher, especially and we had that
great theater at Kelso, too. um like
your your space of like just your uh
your personhood, you know, that that
people felt comfortable in. It extended,
you know, like it extended to that
theater there. Just like a car when
we're driving, like you can kind of you
can kind of sense the edges of where
your bumpers are. You kind of know where
everything is. It kind of becomes you in
a sense like the room you're in if you
know if you're a powerfully um if you're
a powerful being that like allows other
people to to feel safe in that
environment like you you became that
that that stage too, man.
Yeah, you're right. And and what's
really interesting is I mean, you know,
we always met in that back room first,
but then once we got to the stage,
everything kind of came to life. And as
kids grew confident, you know, they
started doing some magical things there.
You know, they just felt really good in
their own skin. They just started
creating things. And man, we we saw some
magical things on that stage. Like I was
in Bend a couple of weeks ago and I saw
this they had this kind of like
community comedy show where this guy
kind of organized and at at the end they
had this group of of uh improv people,
you know, they went up there and they
would throw out some kind of idea and do
the improv. Yeah. And the whole time I
kept on thinking, you know what? If they
could have just seen these kids at
Kelso, I don't know, 20 years ago or
whatever, how many years ago it was,
they could realize that they look like
amateurs up there, even though they are
these older people that, you know,
that's their thing, right? That's what
they do for fun, right? And they had
this kind of little uh improv troop they
had a kind of a cute name for. But man,
some of the things that happened on that
stage was just amazing. I mean, to this
day, when I go and see any kind of play
or anything, I realize just how close I
got to almost being professional even.
It was just it's scary. Yeah. The the
natural talent I I think back like some
of those guys that were in that class,
like I I mean, they're just awesome guys
anyway, but like just the the talent
that was displayed. And I remember so we
did um I can't remember if it was my
senior year or my junior year, but it
was it was one of your times we did a
like a like 10 skits or something. It
was basically like an a a improv night,
but there were skits, SNL kind of thing.
It was like a variety show. We we
included the choir. Yeah. They they did
musical numbers in between. Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, thinking back to that, I I mean,
I maybe if I watched a video, it
wouldn't be as as gut bustingly funny,
but I think I feel like those were some
really funny skits. Like those guys were
smart, man. They we had some funny stuff
in there. Yeah. You know what's really
interesting? You know, those were in the
days when we had these things called
rubrics, right?
And I don't know if you remember this or
not or I was even doing this at the time
when cuz you know that I was there eight
years so there's a stretch of people
right um so I had these rubrics and you
know you it was you know you you would
rate whatever their skid or whatever
performance they did from one to four
and of course beforehand I introduced
the rubric and what I was looking for
and kids over and over again hit the
fours right I mean it was not a stretch
for them because like you said there was
so much talent there and I seem to be
able to bring it out, right? But I kept
on saying to myself, okay, we have these
rubrics to go by. So, and all the kids
are pretty, you know, sure that they can
meet these rubrics. Very few even got
threes. I mean, everything was just
coming out was dynamic. But then I
started I got this inspiration. I was
like, you know what? I want to take it
to another level. Can I take it to
another level? So, I come up with this
idea. It just came to me. I mean, I
don't know what inspired it other than I
just wanted to take it to another level
to start giving out
fives once in a while. And I and when I
gave out a five, kids would go, "A five,
but it only goes to four." And I go,
"When you get a five, that means you did
something extraordinarily amazing." And
and they go, "Well, so then afterwards
people go, well, we should have a rubric
for a five, you know, so we know how to
achieve that." I go, "No, when you when
everybody sees the five, everybody will
know it." And I will definitely know it
because, you know, I'm a trained eye.
But I said, 'It'll be so overwhelmingly
cool and amazing and entertaining and
just dynamic that everyone will know,
hey, that's a five. Y and of course, I
started giving kids instant feedback
after they did skits, so the other kids
could hear me say what I was going to
say, and I never rarely said anything
negative at all. So after a while these
kids kept coming to me man did I get a
five? Did I get a five? And the next
thing I know the level which was already
high went to this stratosphere. It went
to the strat I think you had already
graduated actually when I had come up
with this inspiration and I was seeing
some magical things. I mean it was just
it would and they were like trying to
top each other. It was like oh my gosh I
got to get a five. I got to get a five.
you know up. Yeah. And and and it was
pretty pretty special period of time
there. Well, it's I mean it's it's so
crazy to it really is fascinating to
raise the bar and realize
how valiantly and wonderfully people
will will rise raise right to it. You
know what I mean? Like uh it reminds me
of the Travis Pastana. He was the first
one to land the first backflip on a on a
BMX or a a dirt bike. I know. I know who
he is. Yeah. Yeah. And then so you know
right after that within weeks, days or
whatever it was, everyone's nailing back
flips. It's like you know the four
fourminute mile same thing, right? And
it is it is so cool that by being
inspiring, by just being encouraging, by
like saying, "Hey, I think you could do
better." And they're like, "Okay, I
guess we'll try to do better." And every
was like, "We could we could do better."
It's exciting. It's it's it's uh
contagious, you know.
It's it's it's very fun to be inspiring
and encouraging. And I'm sure your
attitude as the teacher, even when
you're out of earshot, I bet you the the
peer-to-peer conversation was like
fairly encouraging as well. Yeah, the
word of mouth there was amazing. It got
to the point where there was so many
kids in the class, it's like we had to
start thinking about, okay, maybe we
have to put a waiting list or something.
And what's really weird is I actually
got called into the powers that be, you
know, I won't really go into that too
much. And they actually thought I was
recruiting. So I was like, "No, it's
just that these kids are taking it to
the streets themselves and selling
this." In fact, you know, if the kids
weren't included in the class, someone
were just showing up like I said before,
and I'd have to say, "Hey, why are you
here?" You know, it's like, you know,
you're going to get me in trouble here,
right? Told me I could come. they
thought I was recruiting uh so that I
can make more money, you know. And of
course, I've never been, you know,
monetarily, you know, motivated, you
know. This wasn't about that. This was
just about the magic that came. And what
was really cool about this, I never
really defined what a five was, but
everybody knew where what, you know, I
wanted something better, and that's what
they just kept going for. Yeah. Yeah.
Knowing that it's attainable, knowing
that it's that it's there and that that
you could hit it, you know. It's and
also I think what's fun about acting and
creating
is you know when you're trying to it's
just like jamming with a band like you
know that you could hit that thing where
you guys just get in the groove and
you're going you're like we oh we're
we're in it now you know we're we're
we're making a song we're jamming like
we're we're creating the thing you know
just knowing that it's available um and
knowing that the people around you and
you are collectively working towards it
is that's that's like this guy um uh
Rafe
Oh jeez, I forget his name. Darn it.
Rafe Kelly maybe. Um, he is like a
parkour guy. Uh, you know, like a like
like run running and like jumping and
and doing like tricks and whatever. And
they talk about serious play. And uh he
he breaks down parkour as being serious
play. It's like this athletic endeavor
of people together that they just, you
know, end up they turn the world into a
into a a jungle gym basically. Um, and
and I I like to I think since I heard
about that, I always see other areas
where serious play is a thing. And um,
you know, we're talking about our
teenage years for sure. You know, we
we're we're outside of our adolescence
when we're talking about this, but I
think
even in drama class, in improv class, in
in acting, that's definitely a place for
serious play. Like you can finally set
down the whatever you think you need to
be, whatever. You know, you're mad at
your mom cuz she made you do this and
whatever. You know, you got your teenage
things, but in your class, you get to
set it all down and have some serious
play. You don't have to be yourself so
much. You could just express and have
fun and you could be laughter with your
friends. You know what was really cool
about that whole thing is when I showed
up on the scene and as you know, usually
you have a textbook with the class,
right? And there was no textbook. So
everything that you got, Jacob, I
created pretty much. I mean, I borrowed
some stuff, you know, that I knew like
some of the drama games, but some of
those drama games I come up with myself
and kids would just like, "Okay, what
are we going to do today?" They were
like coming and it got to the point as
every year went by, I had to keep
topping myself. I had to create move,
new games. I had to come up with new
exercises for them to do. Like, you
know, I think, do you remember Uncle
Joe's funeral? We did that elaborate
thing, Uncle Joe's funeral. It doesn't
ring a bell yet, but might. Well,
anyway, so I I come up with these
scenarios. Uncle Joe's funeral,
heroes, bomb shelter, and all these kind
of scenarios, and they all had to create
characters, and we went in this deep
dive, you know, like they created their
own story as it kind of evolved, right,
and created their characters and stuff,
especially like the one the heroes that
was, you know, they had to create their
own superhero. And I told him, you can't
you can't duplicate it. You got to come
up with your own original superhero to
fit into this. And I would give them a
scenario, right? And this I mean, we
would spend I don't know, four or five
weeks doing this thing. And it was just
it was like almost like we produced our
own movie on the stage, you know? And I
just it just kept getting crazy like
that. And then I they come in the next
year and they go, "Okay, what which one
are we going to do this time?" you know,
we did Uncle Joe's funeral because, you
know, the first couple years I used
Uncle Joe's funeral until, you know,
because it was so brilliant, all the
different characters and and and Uncle
Joe's funeral, I kind of gave the
characters, right? And then they had to
choose them and then kind of make the
character their own. But as time went
by, they started creating their own
characters when the scenario. So, so I
just kept building and building and
building. But man, they challenged me to
come up with new stuff all the time, you
know, and it just it's just amazing
because it was kind of a mystery like,
okay, what's he gonna do today? You
know, they would come in, what are we
going to do today? What are we going to
do today? We're all so excited and it
was just like almost overwhelming, but
for some reason, I was able to keep that
challenge and being a kind of a creative
person, it fed into that whole love of
of creating things, right, for me. And
it just kept challenging me, you know,
and I just kept on somehow I delivered.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, it's very inspiring.
I I think I said something like that in
in a message, but from my standpoint
when I was younger, I think I saw you I
I always just loved I admired any adult
who could kind of like break the adult
mold, like the like what we're so
serious and we go to meetings and like I
don't know. For some reason, I had this
like when I was a kid, I just I wanted
to just like you you're playing a game
and you don't know it. like just just
chill out for for a second. Like let's
just, you know, let's just talk. I I had
this like weird thing. And uh I don't
know. I never got that from you. Like it
didn't seem like you were trying to ever
play any games. You were just who you
were. Right. Right. Right. You know,
it's like And here was another thing,
too, is I mean, you got to be honest. I
got the unmotivated and I took the
unmotivated and motivated them, you
know, and it just kept happening over
and over. And then then what what So
here's an example I'm talking about.
Sometimes through word of mouth, I'd get
a guy that really didn't really fit in
there, right? Because I had a certain
type of kid that was kind of flourishing
there. And they would show up and they
would do one of two things. They would
either go, "Oh, I want to check this out
cuz it's kind of fun." Cuz every day in
my class pretty much was fun. And I
don't think any teacher could say their
class was as fun as mine. I'll I'll
stand to the day I die to say that. And
or they would come in and try to bully
me, like, you know, misbehave on
purpose. and do all that and you know
what I would just go okay what's you
know what's this guy about you know and
he would come in and a lot of times it
would be seniors for some reason the
older kid older kids would do
this and the other kids would take this
kid aside and say listen it off this is
Mr. Craig, you're going to respect him.
If you don't want to be here, transfer
out because we want to have fun and
you're delaying our fun. In fact, I
would just say, well, you know, that's
one of the things I would say, well,
we're not going to go to the fun as long
as we're misbehaving. And so, I never
really had to control my class. I'd just
have to say something like that and they
would just police themselves. And it got
to the point where you get a guy like
that, they would police them. They would
police them for me. I wouldn't even have
to go and talk to them. Yeah. And the
the kid would do one of two things. he
would leave or he'd stay. And I'd often
have those those type of kids that would
stay and flourish. And then they would
come up to me on their senior, you know,
when they were graduating and say, "You
know what? I wish I would have taken
this when I was a freshman because it
you taught me so much more than any
other class in a lot of for life skills.
Like I became confident. I you know, I
felt good about myself. I always felt
good when I was in your class. It was
always positive." And I realized that,
you know, me, I have this kind of side
where I pick on others to make myself
feel good. And I didn't have to do that
anymore. What a great class this is. You
know, it's like I wish I would have
taken a long time ago. Yeah. And I got
that over and over. Yeah. That's
powerful, though. I mean, to like be
able to to reach that kid who who
refuses to be reached, you know what I
mean? And and you did it by not not
saying like I'm authority and you need
to do what I say, but you did it by
fostering the environment to where like
you know you're you're I'm going to use
the word cronies. You're cronies
basically like came in like hey man this
place is cool. Like if you lean in it's
like we're going to have some fun here.
Let's do this thing you know. Right.
Right. And you know it was a beautiful
thing because I didn't really have to
you know do any kind of disciplinary
stuff cuz everybody just was like hey we
want to have fun. We get it. Every once
in a while have to remind them, you
know, because as a group they might get
a lot of hand and mainly because when
you're playing, I mean, I'm not going to
re in that too much, right? I wanted the
play to happen, right? Because like you
said, that's what I really accentuated.
And there were certain things that they
love that I didn't do a lot. I made them
special. Like I had this game called
Silent Froz. I don't know if you
remember that one. I don't know. My
memory, man. I'm sorry. I'm sure I had a
blast. Well, anyways, when I say silent,
you just walk around on stage silent and
move. And then I'd say freeze and you'd
have to freeze. If you move, then you'd
have you'd be out in the audience,
right? And if I said bomb, you had to
hit the floor, right? Yes. And that game
was so fun for everybody. They just they
like, "Hey, let's play Silent Froz."
Because, you know, I'd always have two
or three uh you know, things like clump
or up sideways down or something that we
would do to warm up, right? And but
silent frozen bombs I always I'd go in
we're going to do silent frozen bombs
and they would go oh you know they get
they'd start cheering almost right and
there was I can't remember who he was
there was one guy was like like it was
hard to eliminate him but I you know and
of course I had these little tricks it
it it really you know I knew it was my
own creative thing but it was a really a
take off on Simon says in a way. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, okay. So, how do you see in
in retrospect now that you look back or
I mean maybe even during that time you
were you were acutely aware of it. How
do you
see how you taught differently than than
maybe other teachers? And I'm not just
saying like at Kelso High School. I'm
just saying like teachers or like um
anybody with a teaching opportunity to
to young people. Um as a young person,
if that teacher isn't inspired with what
they're doing, it's hard for the the the
the kid doesn't necessarily get
inspired. And I feel like, you know, you
led with your inspiration, like it's
just at the front of your chest, you
know, and that I feel like that's why,
um, I mean, someone like me when I was,
you know, I was was I was a little, you
know, kind of a punk rock kid, like I I
didn't really like other people telling
me what to do, but I would just I was so
willing to do whatever whatever you had
going on, you know. Um, so I I guess I I
wonder
like and I also think about I'm always
thinking about like new teachers who
might be listening like how may maybe
they could approach their their own
teaching life too. Um yeah, I guess
maybe just being inspired as as as a
teacher or a leader versus not being
inspired like like where do you see the
importance of that?
Well, um, you know,
obviously as a student when I was
growing up, I had a role model that I
looked to and you know, at that time, of
course, I never knew I was going to be a
teacher someday, even though this guy
really totally inspired me. And frankly,
when I became a teacher, there's a guy
named by the name of Greg Shook. And
this is I grew up in Southern
California. And this guy looked like
Warren Batty, you know, when he was
rightly good-looking, like Warren Batty.
I don't know if you know anything about
him, but he was kind of a legendary guy
with the women. This guy would I mean,
we'd see him at lunchtime today
sometimes and he had a sports car back
in those days when everybody had these
fuddy duddy cars and he always had his,
you know, it seemed like he was dating a
beautiful woman. And so it was like I
was completely drawn to him. And then
he used to he's taught this thing called
contemporary affairs. And of course this
was during the Vietnam War, so we had a
lot to talk about, right? Uh this shows
you how old I am. But um and he dressed
like I don't know, he look dressed like
um well, he kind of dressed like Steve
McQueen, you know, he was just this cool
guy, right? and he'd walk in and he had
the toe uh some pointed toe boots and
and just everybody was just like, "Wow,
this guy's terrific." And he had this
complete charisma. And so when I became
a teacher, that was kind of my role
model for what I wanted to be. And to
me, it's like even though you have to
have your own style, I kind of borrowed
from him in a certain way. And he was
kind of a rebel. And I've always been
kind of this rebellious guy. I mean, I
gotta tell you that
um I really thought outside the box most
of the time I was teaching there, you
know, when you were in my student and
that didn't go over very well because
when you dare to be different, which is
my lifetime motto and that's what
definitely way Greg Shook was. Um you
become a target for those of the powers
that be and and sometimes it's a green
eye of jealousy, right? And they want to
try to think what's this guy doing?
what's he have you know and for me to
transfer that whole thing even though
Greg Shook was my model and what's
really interesting about him is he would
talk about the Vietnam War and he'd have
all these great insights and we were all
learning and we're all like I couldn't
wait to get to his class right because
it was so exciting but then one day the
administrators came to him and said
where's the books and he started had he
says I'm sorry but I got to take the
books out so we'd have these books and
then we'd start reading the you know the
boring stuff and we're like and then
finally he I think he did it maybe two
class periods and then he when we showed
up the third class period he started
reading the books and he said ah what
the heck and he threw the book against
the wall and just said collect the books
up we're going back the way I want to do
it and you know I mean there's a lot of
risk to that you know and not and I
never had a textbook to go by while I
was there you know I didn't have it all
you know you know mapped out so and you
know when I came to school I had fun,
too. I mean, I was making all of you
guys have fun, too. Not making you. We
You joined in the fun. But, man, that
wasn't like work to me then. I mean,
I've taught other things over the years,
right? A good teacher can teach
anything. But when you bring your own
style and your own creativity and your
own curriculum and your own, it becomes
your baby, right? And you start tweaking
it, you see the results of it. And I
mean, you know, you talk about
somebody's love language and their love
tank being full, you know, like mine is
words of affirmation. I can tell you
what, kids would come in every single
day and give me words of affirmation.
And of course, I would return it, too.
Yeah. I never was negative. I didn't
judge them, you know, and if you're a
teacher and you want to be in that
little box that they put you in, it's
going to be a hard day for you.
And it's getting to the point now, you
know, where teachers hands are kind of
tied. They can't get as close to
students as I once did. I'd like to see
them go back to that. Do you do you see
a world where we might be leaning more
more back into that? I I I don't
actually I see I see it going the other
way. Yeah. I don't In fact, the call the
people that I know that are still
teaching, they just can't wait to get
out. And it used to be such a joy to go
to class and teach people like you and
your sister and you know I can name
constantly you know just down the road
and and there was kids that that were so
unsure of themselves and so not feeling
good about the being in their own skin
and they you know they were getting
picked on you know outside of our class.
They'd come in our class, they were a
different guy. And as time goes by, they
started getting confidence to stand up
to those people. Mhm. And they started
creating things and started getting, you
know, say, "Hey, I can do things." And
there's a lot of former students that
have gone into the creative side or
still trying to figure out a way to
write to make money being creative,
right? That were all in that program at
that time because I know I follow them.
Yeah. Yeah. And the ones that have
walked against it are really unhappy
people, but the ones that stuck stuck to
that are seem to be happy. Well, so when
when you have conversations with people
who are still teaching,
um I don't know. I I I guess I try to
think I was almost afraid that you would
say that actually because I, you know,
you kind of hear that, you can kind of
get it. I mean, I think it be must be so
difficult to be a teacher regardless of
of any subject. Just, you know, I think
of things like technology. I I'm sure
that if if I was a kid, I'm sure that I
would be right now when we have like
chat GPT in these things, I'm sure that
I would be such a smartass to my
teachers about like they're trying to
explain something, but I've got the
answer on my phone from chat GPT. I'm
sure I would, you know, it just it must
be so difficult. Um, so those people
that you talk to, I'm sure they reach
them some ways, right? I'm I'm sure
there's like certain students they
reach. like what uh what do you think
people in today's modern climate are
doing to still reach their students in
some way? Is there anything? Well, I
think that if they make their class
interesting and it has a lot to do with
their subject matter, then that's how
they reach people. If they make it
interesting and fun, that's important.
But unfortunately, when they when they
reach to do that, they have the
administrators tell them, "Well, wait a
second. We have to do these certain
things, right?" And you know this really
they have to really be careful getting
close to kids like it wasn't a problem
before. And um I would have a feeling
that I would have even more trouble with
the powers that be if I was a teacher
today cuz I would there's no way I would
compromise. I'd still be that guy, you
know? Yeah. Yeah. You want me to stop
being human to this person right to
their face cuz it doesn't work on paper.
Like come on.
You know, you got to have the human
element in there, you know? It just be
because we're all robbitons, you know,
just walking around feeling, you know,
waiting for the the the bell to ring,
right? Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. For for what? Like what, you
know, what what's your end goal, you
know, like what's um I I remember back
in those days, you know, we'd be you'd
do our warm up and then we'd have
whatever we were working on at the time
and we'd all like meet in groups and get
ready to create and the next thing you
know, the bell would ring and everybody
like, "Wow, you know, I don't want to go
to my next class." Right? I mean, if you
can get that kind of excitement, uh,
that's a really great thing. And and and
you know what? Those 45 48 minute class
periods or whatever it was might have
drugg on when you were taking algebra,
but they didn't drag on when you were in
my class. They were like, "Oh my
goodness, I want to I want to keep doing
it. I want, you know, I don't want to
stop. It was hard." And I'd say, "Well,
we got to go." You know? Yeah. Yeah. I
mean, if you're interested in something,
it's it's so nice to be able to lean
into it and it's and it's worthwhile,
especially when there's an adult saying
like, "Hey, you're having fun and like
that's what you're supposed to be
doing." Like, it's good that you feel
excited, you know? You don't have to be
nervous about the test that all the
time, you know? Um I I think the
um I I don't know. I I mean, I even
think back. So, I was I for me, it's
very easy to love your class. Like even
before I I just I loved acting and and
and all that stuff. I I feel that um I
mean I felt at home obviously
immediately when I walked in. Everybody
felt that way when they walked in your
class. But it was just super exciting
for me. But even you know uh history for
example was not ever anything. I think
even at a young age I was always very
much like how are you guys so sure that
it happened like this? That is an
insanely like
like what a what a leap. like someone
wrote this down and then you believed
them and then this person wrote that
like history was always something when
people were telling me I'm like are
really that's what happened? But but I
will say there was this gentleman um I
don't know if you ever knew him but he
was around the same time Mr. Clawson uh
he was he was a history teacher there
and I remember like he would show us
videos and he got my
attention
cuz and I I don't want as I'm saying
this I don't want to like incriminate
everything. it's been so many years, but
um he would basically show us world war
or he would show us war movies and he
would pause it at certain points and and
more or less say like that's
That didn't happen. Like he he would
kind of like break it down and tell us
he would give us his personal
experience, show us a little bit of like
what the movies and Hollywood say and
then he would tell us what really
happened and then kind of explain the
the portrayal of like why why it was
said to be this way or hey, you know,
Hollywood is going to obviously add a
romance in there that's going to make
you like focus on these different
things. I remember that stood out to me.
Um because he was, you know, he was
someone who was willing to like kind of
break the thing because he wanted to
teach us something that was like he was
actually passionate about. He wanted to
tell us like what his view of the world
really was. And suddenly when they break
that when they pause the movie and say,
"Hey, that that didn't happen. That was
bullshit." Suddenly you get guys like me
who are paying attention. I wasn't
paying attention before and suddenly I'm
like, "Huh, this guy's being truthful to
us." So I I just think like like any
subject, you know, if the teacher can
kind of there I think there's a reason
why that teacher even began teaching in
the first place, you know, there's like
something that they want to lean into
and express to other people and um yeah,
I don't know. I think as a student, we
we could feel when they're hitting it,
you know, we could feel when they're
when they're on that pulse because we we
get to be a part of that. It's beautiful
thing. Yes. And you know, as we know,
uh, history that we learn in the books,
there's a lot of things in the gray
areas that we're learning now because of
technology. And you can just almost
Google it. And of course, even when you
Google it, you have to go, okay, maybe
this isn't true, too. So, you don't It's
getting to the point now where we were
like, people are rewriting history.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, how much it's such a
kind of a weird sentence and it takes
you down a path that you want to be
careful with, but but how do you know
you could trust those Google results?
You know, like ju just because master
daddy Google says it happened doesn't
mean it was exactly that way, you know,
and and you know, that's just a part of
like getting older and learning about
perspectives and you know, the old like
the the winners of history are the ones
who who write history and and that sort
of stuff. So there's a man in in this
information landscape we have here. It
definitely is I think everyone can
resonate just trying to figure out what
the what the hell is truthful what's
actually going on. But I think the the
best bet for me I'm always I love
trusting my intuition. I love when the
person across from me is is speaking
truthfully and I I sense that they're
speaking truthfully. I love just 100%
allowing that and and trying to like I
don't know. I I like trusting my
intuition is what I'm trying to say. No,
I get it. Yeah. Um, okay. So, leading
off with talking about new teachers. So,
so new time teachers who are coming into
the world of teaching. Um, even people
who maybe think of young people who
might be maybe inspired to try to see
they're saying, "Hey, look, we've got
other teachers who are saying they want
to get out of here. They're they're not
really able to the administrative stuff
is like getting in their way. They're
not able to teach." But you got people
listening right now who are probably
like, "Nah, I don't accept that. I'm
going to find a way to teach these kids.
I'm gonna I'm gonna find my way." Um,
what what words of encouragement might
you have for those people? Well, hey, we
need good teachers. And, you know, I
think if you want to be a teacher, you
really obviously can't be in it for the
money. And you have to really give
something of yourself. Use your own
style. Stay true to yourself. It's
always the best advice that old
Shakespeare to thine own self be true
you know it's like if you feel
comfortable while you're in front of
these kids and you're leading them and
they're looking I mean that's one of the
things that really put a lot of pressure
on me even when I left the campus right
I had eyes watching me and that's a
heavy responsibility you know you have
to be a solid role model for them and in
this day and age of technology you know
obviously you have to embrace technology
you're almost forced to do that and
there's a you know with technology comes
a lot of ways to create you know you
know stuff to supplement what you're
told you have to teach and I think is
you know you go into that creative side
and you create stuff that's fun for the
kids that's engaging or something they
do I mean we learn a lot more through
experience and taking action than we do
by just reading stuff right so um you
know if you can make it an active thing
then I think you'll be successful. And
you know, I don't want to dissuade
people from being teachers at all. I'm
just, you know, I'm disappointed that
it's kind of gotten to that. But I'm
sure there's some wonderful people out
there that want to be teachers that are
going to inspire the next generation of
youth. And hopefully you you got a good
grasp of technology because you
definitely have to have that. And you
know, I mean, I had a little technology
in my class. I was teaching kids how to
do, you know, run the lights and the
sound and all that stuff, but man, that
technology is like archaic compared to
what they have now and and it's actually
easier. So, if you can take that
technology and turn it into some kind of
activities for them to do to where they
can learn through those activities, then
man, you're you're mining some gold.
Yeah. So, that's that's what I would say
would be my advice to them. Yeah. Yeah.
And I think they'll find it. I mean, and
I think that h as we always have as
humans, as a society, is is we as our
technology advances, we we find new ways
to to utilize it and and we come up with
with um ways of solving problems. Not
only do we discover new problems, but we
find ways of solving them in uh creative
creative ways that we never would have
thought of before that technology. It it
expands us. So, I mean, as much as we
want to try to predict it being the same
in a couple years, it might be a whole
new different thing that we can't even
like put into words or or try to uh uh
piece together what what it may look
like with with the AI advancements. It's
it's happening so quickly that I I I'm
sure there's going to be plenty of of
bad about it. I'm sure there's going to
be a lot of negative about it. I'm sure,
you know, we're all still dealing with
the the Tik Tok attention span and we we
all have our own, you know, I I'll sit
there on TikTok myself. I'll sit there
on reels myself. So, you know, I'm I'm
right in the middle of it and
everything, but I I'm optimistic. I I I
think I I'm excited about what the
possibility of our advancements in the
technology will be. Um I hope it doesn't
lead people further into themselves and
less connected with one another. Um but
but we'll see. I I try I try to insert
optimism. You know, I I I would hate to
see a bunch of students just sitting at
home in like their little pods and just
talking to their laptop AI teacher that
day or whatever, you know, just cuz I
got I got so lucky to experience great
teachers face to face that I I couldn't
imagine who I'd be without it. Well,
there's a lot of that going on though
already where they just sit there at
home and they learn, you know, through
the technology. And you know, I had a
granddaughter that was living here for a
while and she was going to the local
school and I mean I was like, "Do you
have any homework?" and she's like, "No,
we you know, we have our we get our
iPads out and they do all their
assignments on there." And and when we
visited the classroom at the beginning
of the year, the teachers much said
that. So, you know, I don't really know
how that looks because it wasn't like
that when I was teaching. But, um, it
just seemed like she was kind of
apathetic to learning, but that was, you
know, that's a singular example, right?
There was probably plenty of kids that
engaged the learning and and were
learning quickly and and creating
amazing things. I mean, it's amazing the
students um nowadays are are creating
things on their own that are going to
shake the earth. Like there's somebody I
think was like 18 or 19 years old and
she commit she figured out a way to to
attack cancer cells that's they're
starting to use now. So, you know,
there's an example what I'm talking
about. She was just like a high school
student. Yeah. Yeah. Incredible. So, you
know, hey Yeah. There Yeah. There's
clearly somebody there was clearly
somebody on her path that like either
encouraged her or lit a fire under her
butt by not encouraging her. Whatever it
was, but you know, it's still going on.
Encouragement or or giving her the
opportunity or, you know, presenting the
information that she needed and she took
that and synthesized it and come up with
this, you know, amazing thing. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, it's exciting, man. I'm I'm
I'm looking forward, like I said, I'm
optimistic. Uh I want to take the time
machine back a little bit if you'll if
you'll join me, sir. Uh hop into the
Delorean. Um, all right. I I I want to
go back to before you were a teacher. I
want to go back to I think I think I'm
kind of wanting to think I want to get
inside your mind before you were a
teacher or like kind of what inspired
you to teach other people or maybe I
think it's probably a natural state of
your being, I would say. And it probably
just seemed inevitable that you would
end up uh, you know, inspiring people in
such a way. Um, but I also love to I
don't know. I just I I want to wrap my
head around where you were at before you
decided to teach before you or or any
instances where you noticed that your
input or your leadership like people are
listening to or you could actually
affect change in other people and going,
you know, I could actually teach people.
I have something worth knowing that I
could effectively teach people. Um I
know that there's one of my rambling
questions that are impossible to answer,
Dave, but No, it's all right. Take me
back, man. What what what was it like
before you started teaching? So, you
know, I always was a really great
student and I liked school and I when I
first got out of high school, uh, you
know, Vietnam was still kind of there,
right? And, um, so we were all waiting
to maybe potentially be drafted and
stuff and so I started going to college
there at Fullerton College in Fullerton,
California, and and I was going to be an
elementary teacher. And man, college for
the first time, I really wasn't prepared
for it. I wasn't mature enough. And so I
ended up dropping out and kind of
putting my dream to the side to be a
teacher
someday. And I think it had a lot to do
with not only that gentleman that I
mentioned, Greg Shook, but also my my
grandmother was a teacher, Laurel Belra.
And I just had this really great
relationship with her and uh
she
um she kind of inspired me to be even
consider that. But when I so I went off
to the
military and a lot of things happened
there in the military when I was there
and it was kind of like that dream of
being a teacher someday got put pushed
aside, right? I was just busy with
raising a family, being m I was married
at the time and I had three children
almost immediately when I was a young
man. And so I was kind of overwhelmed
with being a good father and trying to
raise my family and and provide for my
family. And the military kind of gave me
that sort of
um avenue for where I could, you know,
take care of my family. But then my
whole earth was sha shaken. my um my
wife, my first wife, ended up just
leaving all of us, me and the three kids
to our own designs. And so, you know, I
went from, you know, this happy family
man to this guy that had to take care of
three kids. And I was trying to get my
college degree. And where I was
stationed at, they had this degree
program in this thing called health uh
in healthc care management. And so, I
changed my dream to being a teacher to
working in a hospital, like being in
charge of a hospital. And this program
taught me how to, you know, do all the
things from maintaining a a boiler room
to um uh you know, doing the business
office in a hospital. And so I got my
bachelor's degree in that. And then I
got out of the military after my first
wife died in a automobile accident. Of
course, we were already we were
divorced. She was ex at that time. And
so I knew I permanently had the kids
forever. And I got out of the military
and I got this job as a um carpet
cleaner of all things and I was like
working really late at night and I was
just so disappointed and and my future
really looked bleak. I mean I was just
it was so overwhelming take care of
three young kids by myself as a single
dad. This is in the 80s now that I
didn't really couldn't focus on anything
else even though I did complete my
degree program and got my degree in
healthcare management. So I tried to get
a job in healthcare management and then
I found out I had to have a master's
degree and I went oh my goodness it's
like they wouldn't even even look at my
application almost at that time. There
was just so many people in that field
too and they all had master's degrees.
So I was competing against people I
couldn't compete against. So I I mean I
had to pay the bills. So I kept doing
the carpet cleaning. Well, this one guy
came to me from this church I was
attending. And I told him how frustrated
I was with, you know, and I just didn't
feel like I had any direction. And he
told me, "You know what? You should go
substitute
teach." And I was living in this town
called Riverside at the time. And there
was a school district real close by
called Marino Valley. was connected to
to um March Air Force Base, which is
there in Riverside, right on the
outskirts. And I said, "Oh, you know, I
always wanted to be a teacher, but man,
it's just too late for me. I can't see
myself." He goes, "No, you have a bach
bachelor's degree. All you have to do
is, you know, pass a couple tests and
they'll they'll start hiring you as a
substitute and see what you think." You
know, so I thought, well, there, you
know, okay, I'm going to clean carpets
at night. I'm going to, you know,
substitute teach during the day and then
find try to find some time for my kids
in there too, which so I was pretty
busy. So I started substitute teaching
and almost
immediately I knew I was in my place. I
knew this is what I was meant to be. And
I right away I started connecting with
kids, really troubled kids, too. A lot
of them. It seemed like I do really
better with the kids that have some
angst, you know. Yeah. And um you know,
and the other kids did they, you know, I
mean, it's not that I didn't attract
some of them, too. But basically, the
next thing I know, I mean, they were
hiring me as a substitute to be the
long-term teacher when a teacher like
had to have a baby or something like
that. So for the first two years of my
teaching, I did it as a as a substitute,
but they never knew I was the substitute
because the I was I took the the classes
over and I was basically their teacher.
Yeah. And uh there was a couple I I
started teaching from day one. And
what's really interesting, I am actually
still in contact with that cla that
first class of kids that I taught. Wow.
How how old are they nowish? Uh they're
like well the oldest one is like 52. In
fact, I just went to his wedding this
this um this summer. Yeah, it was a
beautiful thing. And then of course, you
know, he treated me like, you know, I
was royalty while I was there. You know,
him and his new spouse. And you know, he
walked his wife down the aisle and
everything. Well, I I mean, they they
kept on taking pictures of me with each
other. You know, I was a pretty major
part of the of the ceremony. But
anyways, um, so right away I, you know,
I could tell that this was my my jam.
You know, it's like, hey, I found my
place and I got and then I went to Cal
State Sanino and got my teaching
credential and then I ended up getting
my master's degree in special education,
you know, and then eventually I got my
master's degree in teach in teaching.
Uh, so, you know, as I kept going
forward and then I got my first teaching
job, you know, real teaching job, which
I think was getting paid like $10,000.
That that's what they paid teachers back
in those days. Crazy. And yeah, it was
pretty
crazy. And
uh so I just, you know, leaped from
there. And it was never a stretch. I
always felt really natural. Um, I
always, you know, because I was this
kind of rebellious guy that was
creative, I always did things outside
the box and the kids loved it. And so I
just kept getting reinforced, right? And
it just kept going forward and forward
and forward and and now I'm a retired
guy and and that's kind of how I always
knew that I was going to be a teacher
and it just went really well for me. I
mean, what a blessing to find out your
calling. I mean, it was a calling
really. Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. Yeah.
Hey, man. I'm glad you didn't just live
this whole life cleaning carpets. I
mean, you know. Yeah. Can you imagine
that? I mean, I'm sure I wouldn't have
done that. I might have figured out
something. Maybe I got my master in
healthcare management. Yeah. But hey, it
was my destiny. It was my destiny. Can I
can I ask you a little bit about, you
know, you mentioned some hardships
during those times as a single father. I
mean, I'm just picturing you, you know,
trying to to work during the day and
then carpet cleaning at night. Can I ask
you about your mindset around that time?
Did you ever deal with anything like
depression? Um, you know, I talk on this
podcast about I like to talk openly
about things like suicide and stuff so
it's not so stigmatized. Um, did you
deal with with anything like like that
around that time? So, what was really
interesting is um I was actually in a
really good frame of mind
um afterwards after I got through the
adversity. But there was a time when I
was like completely overwhelmed and I
was pretty depressed. And I had this
other guy that came to me and it's
always seems to be somebody is like a I
don't know what you call that, but they
show up the right time and say the right
thing. And he told me he said, "Man,
you're like a ship without a rudder. You
need to sit down and write some goals
out of what could make you happy, right?
And then go about trying to achieve
that. And if you you focus on that, then
you're going to be happy someday. And so
despite the fact that I was probably
severely depressed, of course, I didn't
have a lot of time. I mean, think about
it. I was cleaning carpets at night. I
was substitute teaching during the day.
And then I had to spend some time with
my kids and get some sleep somewhere in
there, too, which is about that time was
maybe three or four hours a night, if
that, you know.
Um, so I wrote down all I started
writing down these goals, right? I
started saying, "Hey, this is what I
want in a, in you know, a spouse, a
future spouse. This is what I want to
do. I want to finish my degree. I want
to get my teaching credential." And I
started like I wrote it down and I
actually put it up somewhere where I
could see it. And little by little, I
started to achieve those things. I got
my degree. I got my credential. I got um
you know an advanced degree. I met a
woman that I fell in love with. That
ticked off all the boxes for a woman
that I was looking for. And that truly
made all the difference in the world
because right away she took on me and my
three children. And so they had a child,
you know, they had a mother which is
really what they needed. And you know, I
was worried that I was never going to be
married again. I never thought anybody
would be with a guy with three kids, you
know? It's like, you know, well, who
would take that burden on? But, and I'm
still married to that woman to this day,
38 years later, which is pretty cool.
And I mean, she made Yeah, she made all
the difference in the world. And that
guy telling me to sit down and write
down my goals and make it visual, you
know, and do some kind of concerted
effort to try to start, you know, start
working on those things. I even had down
what I wanted in a wife. And my this
woman that I met that I'm married to
now, she ticked off all the boxes, man.
She just, you know, it's just she just
everything that I wanted in a woman, she
was it. And luckily enough, I found that
she, you know, fell in love with me,
too. And we we got married. Yeah. So, my
life changed right away. But I'd have to
say my whole
life I was o I I I kind of fought
depression. I pretty much my whole life.
I'd be I'd say it's been maybe in the
last 10 years that I don't really I'm
not depressed anymore. You know what I
mean? Yeah. I mean there was even some
point where I had to take medication
like when I was teaching you even just
to control my impulses you know because
you know when you get into depression
those kind of things about self harm and
all that comes into your mind even
though on the outside looking in people
think you have an idyllic life you know
and you know there's a lot of things
with brain chemistry too that where you
just kind of go why do I you know things
are kind of going good for me why am I
feeling like you know I want to throw it
all away you know and I really had to
fight that impulse to sabotage myself,
right? Yeah. Yeah. So, but I managed to
do that. Well, uh, for one, thanks for
sharing that. I really appreciate you
diving into that. Um, I I love I'm
sticking to what something you said
earlier, a a few minutes before I asked
that, you said something about taking
action. You used the word action. Um,
and it's something I've been thinking a
lot of lat lately about. I've spent I
spent a lot of like the last six, seven
years thinking about, reading about,
listening to, exploring with other
people, self-reflecting, everything to
do with like depression and um how our
culture sees it, how our society sees
it, how we treat it, what causes it. I I
really just spent so much time diving. I
I really I turned my obsessivecompulsive
disorder on depression in myself
basically and just I think about it a
lot. Um I'm kind of I'm on the other
side too. I I don't really consider
myself to be a depressed person. Um I
deal with depression for sure, but um I
think
um and there's power in as much as it's
been useful and important for me to lock
my
door, turn off the TV, and just sit with
myself, journal, explore, um you know,
figure out what the hell is going on,
right?
But I really really and especially those
last like year I think action getting
outside of wallowing in my self-pity in
my apartment getting outside of trying
to fix myself all the time trying to
realizing that I've just been telling
myself that I'm Alan Watts has this the
backwards law you know um it is an act
of telling yourself that there's
something wrong with you by consistently
trying to fix something about yourself
right it's kind of this mind bender you
know and I'm I'm never trying to say
like wow your depression isn't real. You
know, you're feeling what you're
feeling. But I think there is this
magical, beautiful
uh warm blanket of action of opening the
door and seeing um you know, you've
probably heard this too, Dave, like you
know, all spiritual teachers tell us
like serve others. That that's the way
out. Like if you can find someone who
needs help and you could help them,
suddenly you realize it's been hours
since you've been thinking about
yourself and your depression and and
whatever. You're in action. So, um I I
guess um I don't know. Does that spark
anything for you? Like like the
actionable act of getting out of our own
minds? Like do do you see that as a
genuine like I think that's like a
secret of the universe or something?
There's something really magical about
that trying to trying to take action. I
think you hit on it really, you know,
majorly when you said something about
service. I mean, I pretty much my whole
life was in service to other people. I
was a teacher for over 30
years. And every day that I came in,
they filled my love, you know, I mean,
they just told me words of affirmation
about how great I was. I mean, and then
you start weighing that out about, okay,
am I really depressed? I mean, all these
people like what we're doing here,
right? And, you know, so I didn't really
think about all that much and I was
really having a good time and I'd have
to say generally I was happy. Um, and
now even when I'm retired, I don't think
I've ever really been happier because
I'm doing things. And that's what you
said, action, right? And and I and
here's another thing is I've been
helping others. I I've been spending a
lot of time with other people now. And
I've changed from being a deliverer of
information to someone that listens to
people and observes them. And I don't
give them advice unless they ask for
it. You know, sometimes I just say,
"Well, what do you think?" And then they
start saying, "Well, this is what I
think." And I said, "Okay, take action."
and the next thing you know they're
they're okay, right? And uh so yeah,
service to others is really key. I mean,
right now I am I'm on a board of a uh
it's a ministry um and they work with
people with addictions. Um, and so I've
kind of become an adviser to this whole
group and it was kind of it needed to be
kind of
like I don't know operated more
successfully or it needed to have its
rough edges sanded. And so that's kind
of what I've been doing. And as a
byproduct I've been interacting with
addicts and I've been kind of a
spiritual adviser to them. I mean, I
have them call me a lot and really all
I've ever done for them is just listen
to them, right? And a lot of them are
doing a lot of good things. And you
know, and of course, as an addicted
person, you always have to worry about
going back to your addiction, right? So,
there's that, too. And one thing I don't
do, and I never did when I was a
teacher, I didn't really judge people,
you know, and you know, I just I just
try to accept them. And what's really
interesting is, and this is true about
kids, if you if you're not genuine, they
they sniff out the Oh,
quickly. And and and it's like, so
that's where my success was. They knew
that the love that I showed them was
genuine. And now that I'm working with
addicts, they can tell that I I'm I
truly love them and I care about them.
And that's not easy to communicate
people, especially when everybody's so
self-absorbed, you know, but you're
right. If you step outside yourself and
you do things for others, you don't got
time to think about your own problems,
man. Yeah. Or you hear these other
people that are like, you go, "Oh my
gosh." And not only do you is your life
going, you know, sour, but you keep
making decisions that make things worse,
you know? And when you when you you when
you're hearing those stories, you're
like, man, my life is fantastic. I mean,
you know, it's like and it really is
fantastic. If I look at my life, it's
like, oh my goodness, how could I
complain, you know? Yeah. And uh but it
truly, you know, I've lived a life of
service like you said and
uh and you know, I just I think that is
the key. It really is. Yeah. Yeah. I I I
think so, too. I mean, there's a that's
like I said, you know, there's all these
spiritual adviserss, all these spiritual
teachers, they have some way of kind of
telling us that. And um it's I've heard
it. I've heard it. I've heard it. And
then I start taking action in my own
life and doing things that I'm genuinely
lit up by that I know that are helping
other people cuz like I like like you
mentioned earlier, you know, you get the
messages. I I I have my version of that,
you know, and so I can see firsthand
like, okay, this thing that took me all
this time and I made it and like
hopefully it was worth it. Well, even
though I didn't get it for the response,
I did it because I is something
fulfilling for me to do. Um it does feel
good for for someone to say like hey man
that thing you said impacted me like
that that helped me understand my
situation I'm going through. It's like
ah okay like one one person was
positively affected by that. Like that
feels really good. It's it's it's
reaffirming you know. Yeah it is
reaffirming. But you know what's really
interesting is you do it out of
self-sacrifice and you do it to help
that person out of genuine care. And
like I said if if you're not genuine
they're going to sniff that out, right?
because they know what fake looks like,
right? Fake concern and all that stuff
and they're used to people letting them
down. But that's another thing, too.
I've been consistent in, you know, lots
of people's lives and so they know I'm
going to be around. You know, they can
call me anytime I want. I don't say,
"Oh, hey, I'm too busy or anything like
that," you know, and if you go about
doing that and have that
attitude, the reaffirming stuff comes
almost naturally. they start telling you
that, you know, like when I was a
teacher, I mean, I didn't ask for them
people to say, "Hey, you're you're my
favorite teacher and I love you." And
and I'm having 50-y old men tell me
that, you know? I mean, I'm having
people that they're in their 40s and 30s
who I'm long removed from that look,
man, he really influenced my life. I
mean, how reaffirming is that? Yeah. And
it wasn't about attaining money. It
wasn't about taining recognition. And
because I did things outside the box and
and and kind of was a rebel and kind of
just threw myself at everything that
came with risk, you know, it made me a
target for, you know, you got a lot of
people there want to like, okay, I want
to take this guy down, you know. Yeah.
And unfortunately, there's people like
that. But, you know, when you when you
serve others and like you said, it feels
good inside when you see the results of
that. I mean, seeing you do this
podcast, what a great I'm living
vicariously through you, man. I mean,
you were on my stage. Now you're on your
own stage, right? I mean, what better
thing that could that be for me
reinforcing what I did was was right for
you, right? You know, maybe maybe just a
small part, but hey, who cares, right?
You never know. You never know how
you're going to influence people. I have
this thing. It's like a theory. It's
called matrix of influence. I call it
the matrix of influence.
So what I always wanted to do is I
always wanted to and I truly thought
about this even from the very beginning.
I wanted to put this guy David Craig
into everybody's life and who he was
about and what he represented. And when
they took my class or they had some kind
of, you know, connection with me in some
way, I wanted them to take that little
piece of
me out into the world, right? And I
never knew if it was going to work or
not. So I just was always myself and I
always brought what I could bring and
was creating and just providing them the
opportunity to excel and through their
success they ended up taking it or
leaving it right I mean sometimes they
weren't as influenced by me but I always
try to be positive no
judgments you know just be humble and
show them love and then they go out in
the world and take a little bit of Dave
Craig with them right and in a way it's
kind only way you can have any kind of
this kind of a taste of immortality
because you know I mean like I said I
have 50-year-old people that really
still think see me as a significant
person in their lives and so what I set
out a long time ago over third like
almost 40 years ago has really come to
fruition through the lives of other
people and I'm hoping that they're going
to take that little piece that I gave
them and they're going to spread that
little piece of Dave Craig everywhere.
Yeah. And and it's like a matrix of
influence. It's kind of like, you know,
I influenced I'm sure I influenced
thousands of thousands of people and
then those thousands of people take a
little bit of what I do into the world
to somebody else and then they take it
and you know there's probably people
that I don't even know that have been
influenced by me. Yeah. I'm the setting.
Oh, guaranteed. Yeah. Yeah. The the
ripples of influence. What do you call
it? The matrix. Matrix. Matrix of
influence is what I Matrix of influence.
I love that, man. I think that's so
powerful. I I love to really think
about Yeah. I'm think about I mentioned
my my buddy not splashing that guy with
with water with his truck, you know? I
mean, maybe that guy went out and he did
something nice for somebody else or, you
know, he's in a little bit better mood,
you know. reality is this that really is
what's going on here, you know, like we
we are very powerful with each of our
interactions and um it's it's like
self-expression and just being able to
open as yourself is just people are
drawn to it, you know, and like you
said, students and kids especially, they
they can tell when you're when you're
bullshitting. They they've got
intuitions that we can't put into words.
They're before words even happen, man.
We're communicating. There's so much
communication happening without the
words. So if you just try to say, "Hey,
all that stuff isn't real, but the words
I'm saying are real." Kids are like,
"Okay, you're doing that thing where you
lie to me, and I'm what am I supposed to
do? Like, I'm playing with your game, or
am I pretending you're being truthful?"
Kids are so smart like that, you know?
Yeah. Yeah, they are. Yeah. I mean, we
had so many wicked smart kids on my
stage. It was just crazy. I mean, there
was so much talent. The place was oozing
with talent almost the whole time I was
there. It just and you know I gave them
the opportunity to start showing their
talent and stuff you know and that whole
thing it was and I don't know why it
came to
me like one of my favorite poets is
Robert Frost and he wrote the road not
taken right
yeah so the road not taken is real
famous about the going to the path and
he took the one that's less traveled and
made all the difference so the dare to
be different which was originally you
know my creation right I knew I had to
have some kind of thing for people to
latch on to. I made those had those
shirts made of actually through Alysia
Huckabe who whose dad's Rick made the
shirts for me and had the drama, you
know, comedy and tragedy because there's
always two sides to everything, right?
And then and then I only gave those
t-shirts out when they were in my plays.
That's the only time they got those
t-shirts. Nobody got them. And those
became treasured. Yeah. People because
they realized, hey, you know, I was in
the play and I, you know, g gave them a
little rec recognition. But to have
people take that dare to be different
into the world, which is what I hoped
and really what it was trying to say is,
hey, screw you to all those detractors.
I'm going to do what I want my way. And
you know, when you I told everybody, if
you dare to be different, there's some
risk to that because people want to put
you in a box all the time. And if you
resist that, I mean, all the great
people resisted that. All the people
that created things throughout history,
they resisted that. So, I don't know
what caused me to come up with that
slogan, but that slogan's followed me
throughout my whole life pretty much,
you know, at least for 40 years. Yeah.
And it, you know, I mean, I can say that
to any of the kids that I took there in
the drama program. They know exactly
what that meant to them. Yeah. Yeah. No,
it's been profound. My sister and I talk
about it all the time. I mean, I
honestly find ways I probably I mean, I
mention you all the time. You've been
mentioned on this podcast multiple
times. I I I bring up the dare to be
different, dare to be different. It had
a profound influence on me. I think I
had this at that time I already had this
natural like I I want to be different. I
think I'm different. I want to I loved
punk, you know, go to warp tour and you
know that's not that punk rock, but to
me it was punk rock at the time. I
remember uh the lead singer of Rise
Against. He was on he was on I thought
they were just the coolest band anyway.
I love their music. They are cool. Yeah.
Yeah, definitely. Uh man, they're so
good. Uh but he was on the stage at Warp
Tour. I remember him like saying things
about the government. He's like, "The
government doesn't want you blah blah
blah." And I remember just being like,
"Dude, you could just say stuff like
that." Like, you're just allowed to I
just I was so inspired by him just being
an artist and like expressing something
that like the other people, you know,
we're not allowed to say that, you know?
It awoke that within me just by seeing
him express who we who he was. So, it
just go ahead. Oh, what I think is
really most brilliant about it is the
kids that I imparted that motto to were
in high school where they were almost
forced to try to conform, right? And
they were trying to find out who they
were, right? And of course, when they
came into my arena, I made them say,
"Hey, be who you want to be, right? It's
you don't have to be. I'm not going to
tell you who to be. You know, I'm going
to give you all these opportunities to
express yourself, but hey." And you
know, and of course, I was the only one
that necessarily judged them. I mean, I
had to give them a grade, right? So, and
I also had to, you know, I'm trying to
make them better actors or whatever,
right? In part that. So, I in some
regards, I had to to judge them and
their performance, but I never really
judged them as people. I accepted them
completely. And, you know, they were
trying to form who they were going to
be. And, you know, I really I think I
gave everybody the confidence of saying,
"Hey, I can be who I want to be." Craig
says, "Dare to be different. I'm darn
it. I don't want to, you know, be like
this guy over here that's, you know,
wearing the same clothes as his buddy
over there or whatever. I don't have to
jump on any trends. I can set my own
trend. I can do what I want. I mean, and
I'm safe to do it in here, you know.
Yeah. And uh and I'm going to take that
off and I a lot of them took that off
into life. I mean, we've had we have a
lot of successful people from that group
of people and you know, I mean, varying
success and then of course, we're not
going to really judge what is success. I
mean, if they're happy, they're happy.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Success. Hey, for me,
man, success is
is liking myself. I'm I'm able to be
myself and like myself. I'm proud proud
of what I'm able to express, you know? I
think that's successful to me. I I never
really had a ton of money or nothing,
but I got a ton of other currency, man.
I got I'm rich in other ways. So, I'm
I'm I'm feel pretty successful myself.
Anyway, what's really weird is
throughout my whole life, I never, you
know, passed money. I mean, if you knew
how much money I spent over the course
of my career back into my classroom,
right? I mean, people would go, "What?
You spent I mean, it's over well over
$100,000." Imagine if I had $100,000
now, I could probably do a lot of fun
things with that. But I poured it back
into my classroom, right? Because I I
didn't want the kids to be without. I
wanted to do these special things. And
it was all about giving to them. And
what's really interesting when I ended
and everything was over, you know, I'm
not a, you know, I'm not teaching
actively anymore. I mean, you always are
a teacher. Um, I was blessed. I mean, I
have enough money to live out the rest
of my whole life and probably leave some
to my kids. I mean, I don't know what
how that happened, but I managed to be
blessed, too. I mean, if you've seen my
house here above the beach in Oregon, I
mean, you would go, "Wow, that's
something a teacher got." you know,
because we you must be honest, they
underpay teachers, but um you know, the
the monetary rewards which are fleeting
anyways come on top of it. So, it's like
when you talk about a happy um relaxed
man, it's me because not only did I get
blessed by all the interactions I had
with all of you, but you know, now in my
golden years, I'm able to enjoy my
golden years like no other time. I mean
I I I you know I'm blessed in all so
many ways. Yeah. You know. Yeah. Well
and you also Go ahead. Go ahead. No.
Monetarily, whatever, possessions, all
that kind of stuff, which really don't
mean much, but you know, a lot of times
people go after the dollar, right?
That's what their career is about. I say
don't don't follow the money. The money
comes. It just comes. I don't know how
it does, but it just does. And you just
have to have the faith to go forward and
do what your muse tells you to do, your
muse. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I've always felt
that money is like the symptom of you
doing, you know, what you want to be
doing. It's like it it'll it just always
seems like it figures itself out. Um I I
want to say so you just mentioned the
muse. I I can't resist that. Have you
read Have you read Steven Presfield's um
The War of Art? Have you heard of that
or or read that book? No, but it sounds
like something I should put on my
reading list. Oh, dude, it's so good.
It's it's a pretty short read, too. Um I
listen to on Audible. He's he's a great
read. He's he's such a great writer,
Steven Presfield, that he takes I
imagine him to just blah his books out
and then he takes every single sentence
and condenses it down into a line of
poetry. That's the way I see it. Like
every sentence stands on its own so
well. Well, he's a great author, but
anyway, he talks about um the muse and
uh as a creator, as um uh you know, an
artist, what what you do is
you yourself out of the way so the muse
can come through. Um yeah, it's it's
it's not so much about just takes you
out of the equation, you know, like it's
it's like you you just remove yourself
and and you get yourself into the
environment like he talks about. He
doesn't wait for inspiration to write.
He he puts himself in an environment to
hear inspiration or whatever because at
9:00 a.m. every day he sits down to
write, you know, and so he he makes
himself like an open open vessel for the
muse to come through by making his
schedule happen. So, um, man, I I want
to explore this a little bit more. The
muse, um, I I will mention this out loud
just because I understand some people
trip it up. I do want to branch into
words like spirituality. I would like to
even talk about God here eventually too.
Um, but I know those are like such heavy
words for people. So, just when I'm
talking about it, know that I'm kind of
talking about like the universe, God,
spirituality, our higher self. I kind of
do clump a lot of these things in and I
just don't want anybody like shut off
this this conversation because I use the
word spirituality. So, just as that
caveat,
um, hey, tell me about like the muse
spirituality like how do you see this?
Do does that ring ring a bell to you at
all? Like you kind of get out of the way
and the muse works through you. Does it
feel like that at all in your
experience? Well, what's really
interesting is it's kind of a frame of
mind that I get into. It's like
sometimes it comes at the most weirdest
times and I it's like I get this urge to
create. So, I really feel like I'm open
to creating all the time, right? And
that being that open to that, it just
the inspiration comes like I was telling
you about Dare to Be Different. It just
kind of that whole idea came to me. And
um I write poetry a lot and um sometimes
I go months without writing poetry and
then all of a sudden it's like I'll
write four or five poems and and it
might be that I listen to Jethro Tol or
something and all of a sudden I want to
write music. I just what something's
been happening lately even though I I've
done this throughout my life. Um, I run
into this guy and he's an interesting
guy and he he's a former vet that's got
PTSD and he
um he struggles with life really hard,
but he's amazing musician. The dude
sounds like Bob, you know, and he sings
like Bob Dylan, which is really kind of
cool. But, uh, him and I, we went to
this thing on Thursday nights. It's kind
of like a place where people create.
Creative minds called to create. it's
called. That's cool. And um so we would
sit there and and
he he would go, "Okay, we should write a
song together." And I said, "Okay, let
me you know, let's come up with a
melody." And and we were in this thing
and we're just sitting there and he was
just playing the guitar. And all of a
sudden, this melody came to me. And of
course being a poet and a writer and all
this kind of stuff that I've always been
it the words for the song just came out
like like as we were singing writing the
songs I started writing the lyrics and I
you know kind of hum the the um the
melody that was spinning around in my
head and he started banging it out on
the guitar and next thing we got this
song called Jesus Keeps Us Straight that
we recorded and we performed and
everything else and You know, I mean,
I'm not saying it's a terrific song, but
I think it stands some pretty on its
own, right? And the whole idea is, you
know, I was trying to have a
relationship with this guy that really
needed me. He was looking to me for
advice a lot cuz he struggles with life,
you know, and um, you know, out of that
came the song, you know, so uh, I could
have said, "Nah, I can't write a song."
No, all that stuff, right? and have
self-doubts, but I didn't. I said,
"Yeah, I could write a song. I could do
this." And that's part of the deal, too,
is there really I don't think there's
anything in this this earth, oh, I can't
dunk a basketball, but that if I put my
mind to it, I couldn't achieve. And I've
always had that attitude. And I think,
you know, I've always been a creative
type and a rebellious type, and
inspiration comes to me almost
constantly.
I mean, I got books and books and books
of poetry that I've written down, and I
don't really care if people think it's
good or not. It doesn't matter, you
know? It's just that I have the urge and
I can't resist it. I have to create.
It's just who I am. So, I've been open
to that pretty much my whole life. I
mean I I mean if you even go back to my
English class back in the 10th or 11th
grade I was writing this poetry beyond
my years you know at least to the you
know the teachers right and so that and
you know and then when you get those
kind of um feedback and you get positive
reinforcement
this is hey maybe I have this talent we
all are so talented at something there
is something that we do really super
good you know and to be open to the fact
that you know to have those those ideas
that we oh I can't do anything or you
know so sort of self-defeating prophecy
kind of words towards ourselves then we
can be open to that muse but if you're
open hey I can do anything I want to do
it's possible I just have to you know
put the pen on down on the paper or I
have to listen to to my brain and it
gives me a melody or um you know I I'm
with somebody else that that has some
talent and we take our talent and create
something together. Yeah. You know,
you're around other creative people.
You're going to create something, man.
You can't help yourself. Yeah. I mean,
we're all listening to our muse then.
And man, some really amazing things can
happen. Look what happened on my stage.
That's kind of what happened. Yeah.
Yeah. You know, Yeah. It reminds me of
um Terrence McKenna has some sort of
quote about uh you know trusting the
universe and you jump off the you jump
off the cliff and you realize it's uh
it's actually just a feathery bed you
know he says nature loves courage and uh
I really believe that and and I really
think I also wonder if you have an um a
perspective on this what about those of
us those of us who are you know deemed
creatives like we we we've touched that
we we we know that like okay I can I can
kind of be this conduit of creation and
make beautiful things and it feels
really right relationship to me. It
feels really like okay I'm doing
something that like I think maybe only I
can do and it feels really you know it's
it's re reassuring reaffirming as I'm
doing all these things. Um, but on the
opposite side, I've also noticed that
that intense energy doesn't just go away
if I'm not creating. It actually kind of
like it can kind of fester in me
actually. If if I don't find creative
outlets, that doesn't mean that my
connection to like this intense energy
stops. I think that I'm just kind of
learn I can be just kind of an intense
guy. And if I don't find ways to express
myself, if I don't find ways to like
write poetry and make music or or do my
art here or um even like I' I've just
I've been on the journey of uh just got
my meditation teacher certification and
so even like filtering my creativity and
my my uh passion into that is just so
fulfilling to me. But um do do you see
or do you think that when creatives
don't have an
outlet but they continue to get that
like intense energy do do you see that
it being being troublesome um do you see
basically I'm saying I think creators
have to create or we really get in our
own heads and we really like get we have
a lot of heaviness that that we carry
around. Do do you see that to be true?
So, so like I said, I'm bombarded
constantly with creativity. So, I either
have to put it down to pen or I have to
create something or or negative things
happen. And you know, I think it's true.
If you look at all the creative types in
the world and and you look at their
personal lives, most of them have trash
personal lives and they, you know, they
they start being on substances and they
get addictions and that ends up
destroying their life. And what's really
bad is when you get if if you don't when
you when all this energy comes your way
and you don't create it does bottle up I
think and then it manifests itself in
negative ways. I mean cuz Yeah, I think
so. And uh that's why so many of them
that are creative types I mean there's a
guy that I mean it just was terrible to
hear his passing. Chris Cornell used to
be the lead singer for Sound Garden.
Great looking guy.
beautiful family he had. Um, what a
storyried career he has. He's one of the
greatest singers I've ever heard. I
mean, let's face it, the dude can sing
and he and he committed suicide. I mean,
it's because he's probably bombarded
with all these what he would call
demons, right? But if you continue to
create, I think, and you release that
energy, then those kind of things don't
happen. you don't turn it in on yourself
cuz that's that's a danger. That's
probably why I've dealt with with
depression my whole life is because
there's been some times in my period of
time where it's like I should have
created and I you know I stagnated.
Yeah. Right. And so, you know, then I
turn everything in on myself, do pity
parties and self-doubt and, you know,
start saying I'm not a good person and
all that kind of stuff. And and then,
you know, luckily luckily I have some
coping mechanisms that got me back on
track, right? But not everybody has
those. And that's what happens to these
tortured artists. you know, they end up
turning things in on themselves and or
they lash out their relationships or
they numb the pain, right? Yeah. Yeah.
Because because when you have all those
those, you know, those things come
hitting you constantly as a creative
person, it's hard to channel it. Yeah. I
I wonder if you had this when you were
younger, did you have uh I had this
weird like uh fan
like the the 27 club? I I had this like
weird so for one I had this and and this
is like a much deeper thing and I've
talked about it on other areas of the
podcast but I I will say I had this kind
of knowing that I was going to be part
of the 27 club. Um I know it's kind of
intense to like just throw on the
conversation but it was just kind of
like I really had to face it. I really
had to like when I dug it out I really
had to be like really look right at it
and go what am I doing? I'm like
thinking this is the coolest thing ever.
Like oh you know they'll really
appreciate me as an artist once I'm
gone. And it was like this weird
obsession with that, you know, Jimmyi
Hendricks and all the and Kurt Cobain
and all these the 27 Club. I'm sure
everybody listening is if they're an
artist, Jim Morrison. Yeah. And so Amy
Wine Amy Wine House now, too. Yeah.
Yeah. And and I don't know and I wonder
if you had this when I was younger
anyway. I definitely don't feel this way
anymore. And I had to really face it and
deal with it and work through all my,
you know, quote unquote demons and stuff
around it. But uh I thought it was so
sick. I thought it was this cool thing.
I I don't know what what it was like. It
was something that I almost wanted to
happen in in this strange way. Um I I
idolized it. I I don't know what it was,
but
um I don't know. Did Did you experience
that at all? I mean, you said you dealt
with like some levels of depression.
You're clearly a creative person. You're
around a lot of creative people. Maybe
even if you didn't, do you see it in
other people, you know, around the ages
of say 18 to 26? Do you see other people
kind of idolize this 27 club? Um I don't
know. What do you think about that? I I
I think you know what's really all of us
are kind of preoccupied with people of
celebrity right famous people and often
especially when you're talking about
people like Kurt Cobain I mean he spoke
to a generation of people I mean he was
pretty influential Jim Morrison spoke to
a generation of people he was a poet his
lyrics are pretty powerful one of the
greatest things I would do in my class I
would teach all the classic styles of
poetry Right. This is when I cuz I had
to teach jinglish along with drama.
Right. And the kids would groan. Oh my
gosh, we have to do poetry. Oh my gosh.
You know, and so then we'd go through
this journey. And there was this one
part in my poetry unit that I had. I
would read them this poetry, you know. I
would just start reading this poetry and
I said, "Well, who do you think this
is?" And you know, they would come up
with all kinds of names. Oh, Robert
Frost. Oh, you know, whatever. Any of
them would say, "Well, I have no idea."
And I say, "It's Tupac Shakur." I say,
"This is Tupac." They're like, "What?
This Tupac? He was a poet." I go, "Yeah,
look at this book." Oh, yeah. You know,
it'll it'll be up here for you to to
borrow if you want. And then I started
sharing some of his poetry. Brilliant
stuff. You know, I mean, he's another
guy had a tragic end, right? But I
think, you know, we're with through that
preoccupation and we think that they're,
you know, everything they do is cool. I
mean, that's why we call fans, right?
It's, you know, you're you're a fan of
them and and fanatic is, you know, the
the shortening of that is really means
fanatic. You're fanatic for these
people. So to, you know, to say that,
hey, I want to be that great. I mean,
these people live in our hearts or minds
or depending on what influence they had
on you. I mean, I'm still remember Jim
Morrison. I listen to the Doors once in
a while. Kurt Cobain, I mean, Nirvana
thing, that was amazing when that
happened. I mean, I was just I mean, I
was I was an older man, but you know, I
mean, I wasn't that old. I was in my
30s, but uh and that was a long time
ago, but man, I mean, he he's just he
was speaking to a whole generation of
people. So, yeah, I I' I'd say we kind
of like glorify that, you know, and I
think we, you know, we look to people
that are icons like that, you know.
Yeah. So that's, you know, I mean,
people are impressionable. They they
want to latch on to something. They want
some direction. They they're not they
don't like looking inside because they
when they look inside like that, then
they find out that they're fragile and
they don't, you know, they don't they're
not talented like Kurt Cobain. I mean,
who could be that talented, you know?
Yeah. It's like you're talking about uh
what's his name? Dave Gro, right? He's
had this famous uh career with the Foo
Fighters. amazing career with them. But
you know what? He's second fiddle to
that guy even higher than him, you know,
in the Stratosphere Rock guys. But um
you know, yeah, I I I think I'm trying
to think of who that would have been for
me. Um I would say it's probably like
maybe James Dean or Yeah. You know,
there's another guy that from a
generation people wanted to be like
James Dean, you know, and he died really
young, too. I don't know. Was it a Was
it Is he a member of the 27 Kobe? He
might be. I feel like he is. I feel like
I've heard his name in that. I bet if we
looked it up, he probably is. Yeah. But
anyways, I'm just saying is every
generation has those people that speak
to them and you know, I mean, I was I've
always interested in music. So Kurt
Cobain, I mean, his I was like, "Wow,
this is this is this is different, you
know. It's like this is so different,
you know." Well, I mean, and at that
time I I could only imagine. I mean, I I
obviously love love Nirvana, but I don't
know that I was like exactly I think I
was too young to like really feel that I
was on the pulse of it. But it sounds
like from what what I hear, it's like,
you know, there's all these these 80s
bands and like they're they're all
kissing the makeup and they're all
performative and they're wearing the
leather pants and then Kurt Cobain came
out with his flannel and was like, "Fuck
that, you know, like and that's sick.
That's That's cool, you know. That's
dressing like that in the Northwest, you
know. There's tons of kids that even
young kids are looking like Kurt Go, you
know. Yep. Dang right. Yeah. I I still
definitely I I wear my flannels and and
people still make I'm here in Texas, but
people like, "Oh, I could see your
Pacific Northwest shining through right
now." Yeah. Yeah. Well, you maybe should
wear your flannel with a cowboy hat.
I'll tell you what. Yep. Yep. I I I
didn't I haven't got a cowboy hat. I
will say that pretty much within a month
I said y'all and now it's just a part of
my vocabulary. I'm I'm a y'all now. It's
I I I say y'all way more than you guys
nowadays. So yeah, y'all. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Um well, so so on on the the 27
club part, I I just wanted to bring that
up. I I just think that um for me
anyway, I think that I was idolizing
kind of the wrong parts of it. I think I
as I started approaching that age
myself, I started thinking of like, oh,
like what have all these ideas and all
these things I want to do and I haven't
done them and and maybe they'll be
looked at if I if I'm gone. And I just I
think that I started idolizing the wrong
parts of it. Um,
when I I could have
been I could have been
idolizing the outcomes of my own
long-term impact. Like instead of like
how much could I get everybody to watch
me before I'm 26, it's like what about
doing a podcast where if I keep doing
this for 20 years, like like you know, I
might be able to really impact some
people over the course of 20 years, you
know, instead of like trying to be
trying to be like the brightest right
now. I want the most attention right to
the top. It's like what about long term?
Just doing what you can day in and day
out like like the long-term benefits.
And I just feel like my mind has
um it has peace there, you know? It's
it's I think a lot of this I got to
prove myself before I turn 27. It has
this like you know this just gripping
this pressure that doesn't need you know
really just need that opening of the
fist like just the allowing of your art
to come through rather than trying to
like catch it all and make everyone look
at it right now you know. Mhm. Yeah. You
know 27 is pretty young. Uh I mean most
of us live to 77 80 or something
nowadays. So 50 years to give up where
you could be creating and influencing
people, you know, just so you could be
the brightest star and then fizzle out.
Yeah. Yeah. You know, to me it just Well
said. Yeah. It's just better to to do
the long to to the long haul. It's more
courageous.
I think so too, man. I think so, too. I
like it. Um, thank you. Thank you for
expressing your your views on that. I I
want to ask you a little bit more about
your spiritual practice. So, uh, not
only your spiritual practice, um, just
kind of your way of centering yourself
and everything, but also if it
correlates, can you tell me about your
ways of,
um, you know, back then and and even now
as you get older, what are your ways
like when you notice that you're kind of
in those spots? Maybe you've had like
maybe um, you notice, oh, okay, I've
been kind of like depressed. I kind of
have been, you know, maybe ignoring the
phone more than I want to or whatever
this looks like for you. How do you pull
yourself out of those times? And then
outside of that, um, even outside of
your break glass in case of emergency
situations, I would love to know kind of
like what your spiritual practice looks
like on a day-to-day basis, like like
what what is that like for you? So, one
of the things that I do and you can call
what at your will, pray or
meditate, and since I've done that, and
I've
also, you know, I mean, you can say what
you will, but I've always been a
Christian person, right? I believe in
Christ. And so I've been every day I
study a different scripture in the Bible
and then try to apply it to my life. And
since I've done that and it's been since
I've retired pretty much and actually
really more intense in the last couple
of years I and along with that I become
more of a listener and observer of
people. But um since I've been doing
those things, studying the scriptures,
praying and
meditating and
unplugging, you know, not like going
right to watch the UFC fights or
something, right? Even though I do enjoy
that, but
um and and kind of spending some time in
nature. Like I took on this sport called
um disc golf and it's kind of like you
go every time you play it, you're out in
nature. And the whole time I'm playing
cuz I'm pretty terrible at disc golf. I
mean, you know, someone would probably
say, "Oh, no. You're pretty good, Dave."
But, you know, compared to some of the
really good ones, I'm really, you know,
way average, right? But, of course, at
68 years old, who cares if I achieve
anything? The bottom line is I'm out in
nature. I'm getting exercise. And that's
another thing, too, is I've been working
on keeping my body more fit. I've been
going to the gym and stuff like that.
And I It sounds really weird, but it is
kind of a spiritual practice. It's it's
disciplining yourself, right? And with
unplugging and disciplining yourself and
studying the scriptures and all that
stuff, all of a sudden I started hearing
like when I'm presented with a problem
or something, I get this little voice in
my head that tells me almost immediately
what I should do. And I've been
listening to that voice and it's made
all the difference in the world. It's
been so powerful for me. Oh my goodness.
And not only what's really cool about it
is I've been able to impart this kind
of way that I'm being and this vibe that
I've I'm sure I'm translating to other
people and it's been helping others too.
And so that's kind of how what I mean by
being spiritual is I've kind of
disciplined myself to a certain degree
to do certain things like complete
change over the way I used to be. And
since I've been doing that, I've been
getting this little spiritual guy in my
brain and I'm not bargaining with them
anymore. You know what I mean? Yeah.
Yeah. And not bargaining anymore. Right
now, I'm listening to them and I'm
taking action. I'm listening and doing
what this little voice is telling me.
Does that voice does that little voice
ever have you do anything like kind of
like I don't know. Is that really what I
should do? Like I mean, you say you you
don't bargain with it, but There was a
time when I bargain with it when I first
started turning towards being more
spiritual, but now I've been listening
to it and nothing better than when you
listen to it and then something great
happens, right? Yeah. And you get that
reinforcement and then you're like,
"Okay, well, why would I bargain with
it? Why would I, you know, start up
saying, "Hey, maybe I shouldn't do
this." No, I I throw caution to the wind
and it hasn't failed me. Now, do you do
you I mean, it kind of just gets into
words, I guess, and it probably severs
something that doesn't need severed, but
So, do you would you call that
intuition? Would you call that like
spirit, soul? Like, do you have any
names or does it matter to you? Is it?
Well, I don't think it really matters.
Even though, you know, in a Christian
point of view would say that, oh, that's
the Holy Spirit, right? But it really
doesn't matter. Frankly, I'm being
guided by whatever's in my brain, right?
And and I think we all, even from a, you
know, from an early age, we really know
what the right thing is to do. It's when
we start like saying, "Well, that
doesn't feel good
or no, you know, that doesn't make me
get recognition or how could I get
more?" Yeah. Yeah. You know, that
doesn't give me any more money or that
maybe I shouldn't listen to that. And we
do that. I mean, as human beings, that's
kind of what we do is we start
bargaining with it and not listening to
that voice. Yeah. Which is telling us
really what we should do. And when we
ignore it, then some consequences could
happen, man. Yeah. Yeah, man. Oh, you
know what I heard the other day? These
people were talking about, it's not
exactly this subject, but I think it
does relay. They were saying um they
asked like the smartest man or like the
person with the highest IQ um or someone
who studies people with with high IQs or
something. Basically, like what is the
difference between someone who is like
high IQ versus low IQ? Um and in the the
sentence that he said was basically the
person with high
IQ does not listen to the voice inside
that says I'm not getting it.
So it's like this constant just like
trust of like just just lean into it.
Like don't second guess yourself. Just
kind of like and I don't know I I it was
crazy when I heard it. I really made me
sit back and contemplate. I was like,
"Wow, that's actually pretty, you know,
and I don't want to make any big
theories about IQ and and I think
there's a whole discussion about IQ that
doesn't really even fit in here, but
it's just as far as us trusting like
that little voice and not trying to I
love how you said don't bargain with it,
you don't bargain with it." I think
there's something really powerful about
that. Yeah. Just as soon as you don't
listen to it and you start bargaining
with it, chances are you're going to
make a bad decision. Be honest with you.
And then you're consequences. And then
life beat you up. And when life beat you
up and you learned the lesson and if you
would just listen to your voice, then
you would have avoided that lesson.
Yeah. Yeah. There's there's something
about it. And I think it also is
something just like when you make
promises to yourself and you follow
through with them, you're able to trust
yourself more. I think when you like
commit to following that voice and you
kind of trust that voice, it just
becomes more intuitive to follow as
well. I think there's there's something
pretty sick about that that happens as
well. Yes. Yeah. Very powerful. very
powerful. Well, so Dave, I just want to
My sister is listening as far as my
knowledge. Um, timewise, if you're
willing, I would love to kind of float
into I did uh promise a Q&A to those who
might be tuning in. Hello nerds. I hope
you're enjoying the episode. If you'd
like to listen to the last bit of Q&A,
it's 40 minutes of Q&A. It's wonderful.
It ties a bow on everything. It's on my
YouTube channel, The Junkyard Love
Podcast, Junkyard Love, and Jacob FTI,
Jacob from the Internet. Go check it
out. Please hit subscribe, follow, all
that. Hit the notification thing. It
helps me out. If you liked any of this
stuff, share it. I will never copyright
you. If you want to clip any of my
stuff, do it. Clip it. Share it. Cheers.
We'll see you next episode. Reality is
[Music]
Junkyard Love again.